Folks have always called me a daydreamer.
Hey!
Where are you off to?
I am delivering seaweed to Futaba
in Nakajima Honmachi.
It is usually my brother's job, but he has a cold.
So... I must fulfill... his...
Ain't you the polite one! No need, no need.
Sorry 'bout the mess, I just finished
hauling some gravel.
After my errands, I'm buying treats
for my brother and sister.
Are you, now?
Take a look. We're almost there.
Hey, quit looking off into space!
Hello?
Wow! Christmas!
Chocolate costs 10 sen.
Big box of caramel, 10 sen.
Half box, 5 sen.
A yo-yo costs 10 sen.
Yeah! Just like that!
Let's get the red one.
Business is still busy.
Thank you for coming. Take care.
I got lost in the city,
and then I met this man.
Suzu-chan,
what's that thing?
A monster.
Huh?
That's what he told me.
He lent me his telescope
and told me to find my way.
Wow! I can see so clearly.
Then I fell into his basket
and met an older boy there.
He's a kidnapper and we're being kidnapped.
What?!
That's no good.
I have to feed the chickens before it gets dark.
And I gotta ride the train back home with my dad.
Oh, me too, me too.
I have to go home before nightfall, or else.
Or else what?
You'll see soon enough.
Hey, mister.
Ouch!
What's this? Take a look.
Let's have a look-see.
When night falls, he goes right to sleep.
Too bad he'll miss out on his supper.
Thanks, Urano Suzu!
What? How do you know my name?
“Thanks, Urano Suzu!”
Hey! Keep it down!
I'm a bit of a scatterbrain,
so I was probably daydreaming that day too.
The waves were wild just last night,
but now it's all gone with the spring tide.
It's the first time we're crossing the sea
all on our own! This is fun!
Let's review. First, I'm gonna give our grandma,
aunt, and uncle a proper “good morning.”
Then I say, “Mom and Dad are stopping by town,
so they'll be late.”
“We brought you watermelon.”
C'mon, I wanna hold the watermelon!
Quiet!
Here! We ain't got time to play around!
My brother was quite the stern type.
Wait—
Good morning.
Mom and Dad are, uh...
We...
We brought you watermelon.
Why, thank you!
Let's take some along as an offering.
My, what a lovely young lady you are.
Grandma always waits for us
with the new kimonos she sews every year.
Mom and Dad joined us after shopping,
and we visited our family grave.
How's life over in Eba?
Can't say it's all rosy.
There's word of a new shipyard.
Is that so?
...rats, in the middle of the day?
There are ups and downs...
But it's not all bad, being young.
I think it lets you see different things.
H-Hello.
Um...
Would you like some more?
Grandma!
Come on. The tide is pulling out.
Come on. Get ready.
Hey, you too, Sumi.
Hey!
She'll come and eat it later.
'Kay. Then do you think...
if I leave my kimono,
she'll come and take that too?
You're such a sweet child, Suzu-chan.
“Must've been a house spirit.
My teacher told us about them.”
That's how my brother explained it to me later.
That evening, everything looked
faintly mellow.
What?! You left your kimono in Kusatsu?
Swim back and get it right now!
Stupid!
And so I forgot how scary
my ogre brother could be.
Suzu, put it lower. The wind could blow it away.
'Kay.
Oh, Mom, can you give me two sen?
I lost my pencil.
Wait for your allowance.
Quit all that scribblin'
and you'd make it to then just fine.
Sumi-chan, let's trade pencils.
No.
Suzu, does Mizuhara Tetsu-kun
come to school every day?
Um, yes, he does.
It's freezing!
You're cold!
So cold!
Oh.
So short!
I hope it'll last the week.
Best be sure not to lose this one too.
Today's art class is free drawing time.
You may leave when you hand your art in.
Yes, sir!
I wonder what we should draw.
Yeah...
Mmm. Very nice.
Impressive as always, Urano.
I wish I could draw like you, Suzu-chan.
I'm home.
Well, I'm off to get some pine needles
for kindling.
Thank you, dear.
Mizuhara-san, you won't be able to go home
until you finish drawing.
Don't want to.
My folks quit workin’ with seaweed
and picked up drinking instead.
I hate the ocean.
I won't draw it.
Urano, give me your hand.
Huh?
What?
Take it.
What? But...
It was my brother's.
He's got plenty more.
The rabbits are hoppin’ about today.
The sea was like this back at New Year's,
when the ferry capsized.
You can draw for me if that's your fancy.
Even if it's just this boring ocean.
Mizuhara-san, what did you mean earlier?
Huh?
Oh...
The white waves look like rabbits hopping.
Mizuhara-san, you can have my brother
if you want.
No thanks.
All the guys say you should run
when you see your brother.
But still,
he's better than the idiot
who joined the Navy and drowned.
Hey, you're right,
they do look like white rabbits.
I'm done.
Here you go.
T-Thanks...
You shouldn't have bothered.
Now I have to go home.
And with a drawing like this,
I can't hate the ocean anymore.
Imperial Navy Forces conducting operations
in the Eastern Pacific...
Hurray! Hurray! Hurray!
Morita's girl! There's better pickings over here.
Gotcha.
My.
That's some lovely battledress you have on.
Whoa, that's cold!
You've gotten quite good.
We'll have lunch when you're ready.
I'm ready!
That's far!
You're going far away
to get married, Suzu-neechan.
I am?
You're staying near, Sumi-neechan.
They say a girl who holds their chopsticks
at the ends wed far away.
Really?
Where did you come from, Grandma?
I came from Furue.
That's just one village over.
Women who end up in Manchuria
must be using fire tongs to eat.
Says Urano Sumi, as she shifts her grip
on her chopsticks.
There's no adventure in marrying close to home.
Suzu-chan, you need to go straight home!
I just got a call.
A boy's come all the way from Kure
looking for your hand in marriage.
Kure?
Suzu-chan, how old are you?
Nineteen. Well, actually, eighteen.
You can always turn him down if you want,
but at least go and meet him.
Suzu-chan, come here a minute.
I want you to have this.
I fixed it up for the day you get married.
I hope it all works out for you, sweetie.
Thank you.
The wedding will be at the groom's house, right?
Right.
On your wedding night, he'll ask,
“Did you bring an umbrella?”
You'll answer, “I brought a brand new one.”
Then he will ask, “Can I open it?”
You must answer, “Please do.”
B-But why?
Because you must.
I guess I'm becoming an adult.
I think Kure is where there's a naval port
that's full of sailors.
What? Mizuhara-san?
I-It's been a while.
Hurry on home.
Huh?
Your ma was so shocked
that everyone around here knows
after all that noise she kicked up.
Oh, gosh!
I thought you were the suitor!
You dimwit!
I just came home for my brother's memorial!
The guy ain't someone you know?
Never met him.
Maybe he has me confused with Sumi-chan.
She's much prettier than I am.
I wouldn't say that.
So I guess my son took a shine to your daughter
on his way to school.
But, uh, it wasn't easy to find your house.
We lost the seaweed business
to land reclamation three years ago.
She'll be home any minute.
Okay.
I don't know if I should marry him or not.
Here you go.
But I wonder, why did I
taste caramel in my mouth?
It's so cold.
Now what should I do?
She said I could turn him down if I want to,
but I don't even know if I like him or not.
Excuse me.
Yes?
We lost our way.
Which way is the station?
It's this way.
Thank you.
A nice sailor showed us the way before, but...
Oh, him? He's an odd one, you see.
They said a strange woman in the woods
showed them the way.
Have I just been daydreaming all this time?
How did this all happen so quickly?
Lookin' okay, right?
Please close the blinds facing the ocean.
Yeah...
Someone left a window open.
Kure.
The Naval artillery must be doing drills.
Our deepest apologies.
That charcoal bus
couldn't climb this hill, could it?
Oh, Kobayashi-san.
Oh, hello.
Thank you for having us today, Kobayashi-san.
I'm glad the weather is nice.
I'm forever thankful for your kindness.
Though lacking in my ways, I will do my best
to be a faithful daughter-in-law.
I'm Kobayashi, Shusaku's aunt.
I'll be your matchmaker for today.
You do know your husband-to-be's
last name, right?
Definitely lacking in many ways.
Are you really going to be okay?
We've climbed so high up!
They live on the very corner.
Here we are.
They're here!
My apologies for such a simple wedding.
Simple is best for my daughter.
Suzu-chan.
Oh no!
My beautiful kimono is all covered up.
Suzu, no!
Don't disrobe here!
This is quite the feast!
I'm sorry her brother couldn't come.
Would you just look at all this!
Well, you did provide us
with the ingredients, Urano-san.
This includes supper as well, so make sure to eat up.
This stew is delicious.
I'm glad. He seems the quiet sort.
No one would be noisy at a wedding.
You sure were though!
You were though!
See you when you come home to visit!
I'll see you then!
I'll see you around.
Let's see... who was that?
Now that she's here,
you can relax a little bit and have her take over.
I will.
Father, Mother, it's an honor
to be part of your family.
The honor is ours.
I have a bad leg,
so I'm counting on you, Suzu-san.
Yes, ma'am.
Sorry you have to do that.
It always gets burnt
when Keiko does the cooking.
Oh, right! She's my sister-in-law
who's already married!
The navy's doing searchlight drills.
Where have I ended up?
Thank you for setting the futon.
Sure.
Oh, Suzu-san?
Yes?
Did you bring an umbrella with you?
Yes, I did.
It's brand new.
May I borrow it?
Here.
Boy, I'm starving.
What's wrong? Is yours not ripe?
You didn't eat at the wedding.
I'm just glad you've got a mouth that works.
You don't have to worry about that.
I just swallowed the entire fruit.
With my mouth.
Um, have we met before?
We have. Don't you remember?
I'm sorry. I've kinda always been
a bit of a scatterbrain.
You haven't changed at all since then.
I also remember that beauty mark of yours.
The neighborhood here shares the same well
a little ways down from our place.
“Ho-u-jo.”
Excuse me...
What might be the street name
and number of this house?
Oh, of course!
We're off.
Have a nice day.
Everyone around here
seems to work for the Navy.
Houjo-san?
Houjo-san!
Ah, yes?
“Rationing duty”?
This one and this one
are always going at it.
Nice to meet you.
I'm Chita.
I'm Kariya.
There you go again!
I'm just measuring it.
You're eyeballing it!
No I'm not.
It's unfair.
No it's not.
Unbelievable.
What is?
You and your ways.
What ways?
Haha, I'm young, don't worry!
It's gonna fall!
Oops!
Ouch...
I'm so sorry.
I must point out that the probability
is extremely high.
So if there is a firebombing, we must
be prepared to react as quickly as possible.
This is...
Scoot closer, will you?
It's awful chilly in here.
Okay.
This has become my daily life.
Oh, that's Keiko's dress
from when she was younger.
It goes in the storage.
She wore that on her dates with her husband.
They'd go to the cinema,
fancy restaurants, and exhibits.
She was a real modern lady, wasn't she?
Those were the days.
When Shusaku was in the fourth grade,
the disarmament peace treaty
shut down warship production.
My husband and neighbors lost their jobs too.
It was a hard blow.
But that didn't stop Keiko finding a job
and a husband all on her own.
Well! In that case, I'll work just as hard!
We thought those times were tough.
How I miss those days now.
Oh, hello.
I'm home.
Welcome back, Onee-san.
So boring.
How's it boring?
Isn't rice a real luxury these days?
I'm talking about you!
I was expecting you to be one of those
sophisticated city girls from Hiroshima.
So what's with those patched up,
baggy slacks you're wearing?!
Are you roasting beans?
My, if it isn't Harumi-chan. Welcome, dear.
Mommy is mad about everything lately.
So I stay quiet.
I'm sorry, this is all I've got.
Is that so?
Then sew one, right now!
Also, that rice isn't a gift.
It's for me and my daughter, okay?!
What brings you home, Keiko?
Mom, listen to this!
Oh boy. What to do?
Ouch!
Not again! Another mistake.
You'll never get married if you can't do it right.
Fine. Then I won't.
Uh, so at the waist...
Ah, I see.
I undo the seams... and cut.
Put them together... and sew.
Put in a waistband and...
I'm done!
Let's try it!
I'm Kuromura Harumi.
I'm Houjo Suzu. Nice to meet you.
Can I have some string, Suzu-san?
Will this do?
Oops.
Suzu-san, are you going into town?
Yes, to get rations.
I'll go instead.
Hand me your ration coupon and wallet.
Are you sure? Thank you.
Welcome home.
Stop. I'll do it.
Hey, Mom!
I'm coming.
What is it, dear?
What should we do for soup?
Keiko, Harumi, you're here.
Just the two of you?
Welcome home, dad.
Make yourself at home.
What a surprise—Nee-chan didn't burn the rice.
Excuse me, Shusaku?
O-Ouch...
Um, Onee-san...
Thanks to you, I was able to fix my kimono.
My pleasure.
Our mother has a bad leg,
and we brought someone like you
to a place you know nothing about.
It would've been better
if I just stayed here all along.
Suzu-san, why don't you go home to Hiroshima?
What?
That'd be for the best.
I'm home.
Whew! I'm exhausted.
Welcome home.
Oh, it's eight already.
That's quite a pile.
Oh, these are all the thousand stitch sashes?
That's right. Sumi, make sure you stitch them.
Okay.
Come on, Suzu! Wake up already.
Y-Yes!
Here, it's time for dinner.
Oh gosh. I dreamt I married a man in Kure.
Are you awake now?
Yes.
My sister-in-law said I could
go back to Hiroshima.
I was puzzled at first.
Oh, to visit family!
Then my in-laws apologized for
not letting me come visit sooner.
They all told me to relax for a couple of days.
If that's what you want,
then good for you.
So, did you write to Yoichi?
I did.
I haven't heard from him, though.
Have you?
He's stationed far away.
And he doesn't write much.
Suzu might've written down
the wrong address too.
Bath time!
How's the volunteer corps?
I'm getting used to it.
Don't I smell like machine oil?
It must be a dangerous job.
But it's not as cold as harvesting seaweed,
so there are good things about it.
A handsome young officer
slips me his meal tickets.
Oh my!
I think I just accidentally learned
some Army secret!
How about you?
Do you like Kure?
Uh, I don't know yet. There's so much to learn.
I think I might've just unearthed a Navy secret.
W-What is it?
Good night!
Suzu-chan?
Yeah?
You're getting a bald spot.
What?!
See you later, Suzu-chan! I'm off to work.
Once emergency measures start next month,
even short travels will be restricted.
Take care.
I will.
Well, it's time for me to head
to the women's association.
What? You're leaving too?
Dad gave me an allowance.
Goodbye.
Goodbye, Hiroshima.
What?
That's why you came back?
I feel so bad for all the folks in that house.
Oh, I'm home.
My sister-in-law stayed the whole time.
Mommy, can I use the ink?
What for?
Please, I wanna use it.
Suzu-san?
What did you tell Harumi?
Can I take care of the community notices?
Sure.
I'll go now, then.
She's been a bit off since
coming back from Hiroshima.
Leave her be. She's still just a child.
Okay then, thank you for your time.
Come on, please!
I said no!
Lend me the ink brush. Please!
You don't need an ink brush.
Welcome home.
Picking herbs?
Yes. For tonight's supper.
I see.
All the dandelions here are white, aren't they?
Are they different in Eba?
Oh, here's a yellow one.
What?
It might've traveled far to get here.
I was wondering why
you were so gloomy of late.
You're homesick, huh?
No, I'm not.
Look, over there.
They're aircraft carriers.
Maybe it's the Hiyo and the Junyo.
They're big.
Those little ones are destroyers.
There's a U-boat from Germany.
And that ship is a submarine tender.
Look, some white-eyes are flying about.
Oh.
Over there.
Look.
I can see.
Shusaku-san, what is that?
Is that a ship?
That's the Yamato.
The world's greatest warship,
born from the Orient's greatest shipyard.
There's people on it too?
Yes.
About 2,700 people.
Two thousand...
seven hundred?
That's right. Let's welcome them to Kure,
Suzu-san.
They cook for 2,700 people
on that boat every day?
Uh, Suzu-san...
And do laundry?
I-I'm sorry. Are you all right?
Yes.
Are you hurt?
You know, Suzu-san, stressing over your bald spot
will only make you lose more hair.
So you noticed.
Please, let me borrow the ink brush?
I want to paint Suzu-san's head.
I said no! You'll stain everything black.
Aw...
Soon, my sister-in-law left and went back
to her late husband's family, so I thought,
“All right! Now it's my turn to cook!”
But by then, rationing had gotten much worse.
Four dried sardines for three meals
for a family of four.
It's still better then just
being given vegetable leaves,
and maybe I can buy some soy pulp.
Ah, I see.
Violet.
Stellaria.
Field horsetail.
Dandelions, wood sorrel,
dried sardines, soy pulp.
Potatoes, sweet potatoes,
flour, pickled plum pits.
Cut and steam the sweet potatoes.
Blanch and chop some field horsetails.
Mix them with the sweet potatoes and some flour,
and roll into flat disks.
And lunch is ready!
It's so quiet without Keiko.
Leftovers are to be dried and preserved.
And moving on...
Use five times more water
for thin rice porridge.
Add roughly chopped potatoes
and let it simmer for ten minutes.
Then add chopped stellaria.
Cut daikon rinds and dandelion roots into strips,
and cook with soy sauce and sugar.
Add the chopped dandelion leaves,
mix in the soy pulp, then let it simmer.
Finely slice and salt daikon,
then add wood sorrel.
Boil pickled plum pits in water.
Add the dried sardines and stew while basting.
Finish it off with salt to taste.
Oh, so Kariya-san taught you this recipe?
Rice rations were halved, so I made
rice and sweet potato porridge.
You did, eh?
But I'll do even better tomorrow.
The loyal samurai, Kusunoki, devised a recipe
to bulk up ration size during a siege.
First:
Toast and brown some rice.
Add triple the normal amount of water
and gently simmer the rice.
If you're saving rice,
then you have to save energy too.
Leave it to the fireless stove
of the Great Empire of Japan.
Let it sit overnight.
Add miso and violets to
yesterday's sardine stew.
On the stove, reheat the rice to a boil.
And it's done!
Samurai Kusunoki's special,
“Nankomeshi,” is served!
This one is Father's obento.
We have lots of rice today.
The grains are swollen.
I've never seen rice cooked this way.
All right! Let's eat.
Let's eat.
We're off.
I'm sorry.
Samurai Kusunoki must have been a great man indeed
if he gladly stomached food like that.
That's for sure.
Air raid warning!
Air raid alert!
There's nothing on the radio.
Is Shusaku off to work already?
Yes.
Well, estimates of the enemy's range
put only Kyushu in danger for now.
No need to run to the mountains yet.
It's only a blackout.
Don't fall now.
They're tearing houses down now.
They need to build firebreaks
throughout the city.
Oh...
Well, I don't think
we need to worry about that here.
That's terrible.
I hope they can find a place to live.
Oh, thank you.
You're welcome.
If you need firewood, I have plenty.
My house was torn down.
Oh no.
My family's moving to Shimonoseki.
What?
So I figured I might as well break ties with them.
Huh?!
Don't worry. I'll find myself a job
and start working.
It needs to fit a few more people.
Hmm, like this?
Yeah.
I heard shots on Mt. Haigamine yesterday.
I guess there are big guns way up there too.
Things are getting rough.
Thank you for helping us.
Well, thanks again.
Well, this ought to make a nice bomb shelter.
Yeah.
All right!
With all that overtime at work,
he got a bit carried away here, didn't he?
The pillars and tatami mats from
Nee-chan's house were a godsend.
Shusaku, did you place this here?
Oh, that. It was nothing.
Okay, let's clean up out here.
All right...
Shusaku-san, can I have some of this dirt
for the fields?
Sure, take it.
Just be careful, okay?
Oh, so this is where you've been.
Yep. I'm looking at ships.
Made it.
Ah, there's a lot of ships today.
I see two Yamato ships.
One of them is the Musashi.
I see lots of battleships but no aircraft carriers.
Yeah?
Oh, that's the Tone.
She has no rear turrets.
She's an aircraft cruiser.
Really?
I'm amazed. You know so much.
Yeah, Onii-san taught me.
I see.
I also learned a thing or two.
That's a destroyer.
Oh, there's a small one headed this way.
That's a motor launch.
Really?
Well then, I'll teach you something in return.
You see that big cloud?
Yeah.
It's called an anvil cloud.
Okay.
It causes heavy rain.
What?
Ahh! Shusaku-san!
For the moment, just take
whatever you can into the shelter!
Oh, thanks.
I can do it. I can do it.
You really like your battleships, huh?
Huh?
Harumi-san was telling me about them.
Oh...
I didn't teach Harumi.
It was Hi-bo.
He...?
Yeah, Hi-bo loves battleships.
You'll meet him one day.
Is it...
this “Hisao” here?
Yeah.
I can't believe I'm here, doing this with him.
Good.
We can go back in the house,
now that it's only drizzling.
Um...
You're a married couple.
It's nice that you get along.
Isn't that nice? Two married couples
getting along so well.
Keiko...
They used to measure their heights together
as one happy family.
Wait, was her husband...
Even if he tried to,
he'd have been too frail to get drafted.
I guess he was way too skinny.
When my father was rehired
by the Navy Arsenal,
Nee-chan went to buy a watch for him.
That's where they met.
They got married and remodeled
the store together.
But Keiko, with her temper,
didn't get along with his family.
When her husband died,
they fought over the business.
But in the end, the building was torn down,
and everything was gone.
Hisao is the heir of the Kuromura family.
He was taken to Shimonoseki.
As you'd expect, that was hard on her.
I wish we could all smile
and live together in peace.
Me too.
I just need to check on the garden.
It took months for me to learn that about her.
That's how much of a scatterbrain I can be.
That's the Yamato.
And that's Tone.
Sir, um, I was just...
I just wanted to send a drawing
to my nephew.
Does this woman live here?
T-The military police?
What?!
She was sketching shorelines and ships.
That's espionage!
She may look innocent, but who knows
what nefarious plots she's scheming!
Her husband is a two-bit clerk
at the navy court-martial office.
Has she attempted to access military secrets?
Has she sent coded transmissions?
Does she have a random number table?
Is there anything suspicious
regarding her background? Well?
We will not arrest her today,
but keep a close eye on her.
After all, a daughter-in-law is still a stranger!
I'm home.
What's going on? The laundry is still outside.
Oh, Shusaku, it's just that
the military police investigated Suzu-san, and...
Suzu-san, come with me.
It's pretty small, so you won't be able
to draw the shoreline.
Suzu-san, since you love to draw,
can you draw me sometime?
I don't know if I can draw you well...
Suzu-san involved in espionage, huh?
Shusaku, you were lucky.
We had to appear apologetic to those MPs.
So we couldn't laugh or smile.
The harder we held it in, the funnier it got!
As soon as she focuses on something,
her head goes straight up into the clouds!
With her sitting all quiet,
they must've mistook her for someone smart!
S-She thought a court-martial
was a court for only marshals!
What military secrets did they think she was after?
Those Army MPs are idiots!
I don't understand, but it sounds funny!
I wish we could all smile
and live together in peace.
Me too...
I'm home.
Oh, Dad's home! Let's tell him too!
Am I the only one who doesn't find it funny?
Even in war, cicadas cry and butterflies fly.
It's so hot...
Oh no, no more sugar?
We thought the war would hit home soon
when all the air raids happened in June...
Wonder where it is now?
Ouch.
I'm sorry, Harumi-san.
I'm okay.
I was just looking at the ants.
I wonder where they're going.
Sugar's so scarce right now!
We need to hide it from the ants.
But, uh, where?
W-What's wrong?
We thought putting it in the water
would keep the ants away from it.
Here, take this. Buy some at the black market.
Roads I usually don't travel.
Eat up!
They said we're supposed
to be low on everything,
so what's with all these people selling stuff here?
Huh?
This is a fine rice from Taiwan.
I could also arrange for some
homegrown rice, if you want.
Oh my, I thought we weren't
supposed to grow watermelons now.
Wow, they have everything here.
It's like summer breaks before the war.
Sugar's 20 yen a pound.
Huh?! That's fifty times the ration price!
The price is only gonna go up from now on.
With that secret stash mother gave me,
and this month's budget, I only have 25 yen.
Eeny, meeny, miny, moe...
What'll we do?
Sugar might soon cost about 150 yen.
A box of caramel could cost more than 100 yen.
And three pairs of socks might cost 1,000 yen.
How will we be able to survive
in a country like that?
What?
Where the heck am I?
Naganoki? The naval cemetery?
Oh, that's Nagasako.
Oh, isn't it that way?
It's that way.
Oops, I'm sorry.
It's okay.
Watermelon?
Yeah.
Caramel?
You lost?
Yeah.
Even though you're grown up?
Where did you come from?
Naganoki.
Onee-san, no one will give me directions,
and everyone smells real nice.
Is this some fairy tale palace or something?
For Naganoki, you turn that corner,
go down to the post office, and then...
Wait here.
Nee-san, I have a question.
From here, go straight and turn right
when you pass the post office.
Thank you so much.
Many folks in these parts don't really
know their way around.
Most of us aren't locals,
and we don't go beyond these gates.
Are you also from South Hiroshima?
Near the ocean?
I am. But how did you...?
Your accent.
Oh, are you from Eba?
Yeah, from Kusatsu.
Kusatsu!
I had watermelon at my grandma's place
every summer.
We were poor, so I always ate the rinds
people left behind.
I met a kind person once,
and I finally ate the red flesh.
That was a long time ago.
But anyway, you sure can draw.
After looking at them...
Um...
Sure, no problem!
If there's anything else you want me to draw,
just tell me.
Mint candy and warabi-mochi!
Mint candy.
And ice cream with wafers on top.
Wafers?
Not heard of 'em?
You've never been to a coffeehouse?
Rin!
Quit dawdling!
Hey.
Sorry, I have to go.
Oh, I'll draw them up and bring it to you later.
Don't.
You shouldn't come back here.
Huh?
You'll just get lost again!
What took you so long?
Did you somehow forget your way home
from shopping?
Onee-san, what's an ice cream with wafers
that you can get at coffeehouses?
What? You don't know?
Well, it's sweet and cold.
You eat it with something that's
a bit like a crispy rice cracker.
Ah, wonderful...
Oh!
That's...
Talking about desserts for the first time in ages,
somehow makes even water taste sweet.
It's still very hot.
Mrs. Houjo-san.
You've got a phone call.
Yes? A phone call for me?
Ah, this is what he wants.
Ahh, it's so hot.
You'll embarrass Shusaku dressed like that!
We've still got time. Let's take a walk.
So how goes it with the GKF?
They're quite laid back.
That so?
Well, let's go have a cold beer.
Shusaku-san, I've brought your notebook.
Huh?
Oh, Suzu-san?
You're pale as a ghost. Are you okay?
D-Do I really look that funny?
Nah. I'm happy if you're okay.
Well then, let's go.
Huh? What about work?
There's no rush. I just used the notebook
as an excuse to get you down here.
Didn't you tell me that you enjoyed
going out to shop in the city?
What's the matter?
Don't tell me you really aren't feeling well.
I don't want you seeing this silly grin on my face!
I wanted to take you to the cinema, but...
I guess a big ship is back in port.
Sailors do need their time off.
We'll just have to go another day.
Suzu-san?
A classmate of mine from elementary school
became a sailor.
What if I bump into him?
Just say hi like you normally would.
I feel like I might wake up from this dream
if I meet someone from my past.
Dream?
Changing my name and moving was hard for me.
But you've been so kind to me.
And I've made friends.
Waking up now wouldn't be any fun.
I'm just happy to be who I am today.
I see.
Stuff from the past
and the paths we didn't choose to walk.
They're like dreams we woke up from.
Suzu-san, choosing to marry you
was the best decision of my life.
But I am a little worried that you've lost weight.
I suppose I haven't had much of an appetite lately.
Here. Eat for two people!
You had a lot for breakfast,
so this should be enough.
Eating for only one after all.
Ready port entry. Slow ahead. Reduce 2 knots.
Roger. Slow ahead. Reduce 2 knots.
Roger.
I'll go ask for you.
Thanks.
Hello?
Wow, a real sailor!
We bumped into each other at the well.
I'm Mizuhara Tetsu, an Aoba crewmember.
Isn't Aoba a Class A cruiser?
Mind your manners, Harumi.
Hup.
Wow, you're tanned even though it's winter.
So you're here to take a bath?
“Bath shore leave” just means free time.
I had nowhere else to go,
so I thought to call on Suzu,
a friend from back home.
Thank you all for takin’ such good care of Suzu.
Back home, she weren't good for much
but drawing and making seaweed.
She must be quite the wool-gatherer here.
Don't be shy now. Just say the word
and I'll take her right back home!
Stop being so cocky!
And don't call me by my first name!
Huh? What am I s'posed to call you, then?
You ain't Urano no more.
Suzu-san, you can't hit a sailor.
What's so funny?
You. You're so ordinary.
This is good! Real good!
It's nothing special.
This is heaven.
Hey, Suzu, wanna join me?
Are you crazy?
Suzu-san, where's the lamp?
Oh, I think it's in the shelter.
Okay...
I'm gonna be a sailor when I grow up.
That's great.
Upsy-daisy.
Here.
Thank you.
What do you say?
Good night.
Ahh, there's nothing like being on dry land.
Well, I'm turning in for the night.
How's the Aoba?
We got banged up some in Manila
and came limping home.
She's a good ship, but yet again
she didn't get to triumph or sink in glory.
You know, Shusaku-san,
getting left behind by those who've died...
really gets under my skin.
Mizuhara-san, with my father away on duty,
I'm the head of this family.
I'm sorry, but I can't let you sleep under this roof.
Oh?
I asked him to sleep in the shed.
That was quite a sight. I never knew
you had that sharp a tongue.
Here. I tossed some coals
in the bed warmer. Take it to him.
And then you might want
to have a nice, long chat.
You may never see him again.
I'm sorry about the room.
It's paradise compared to a hammock.
Come on, we have lots to catch up on.
It's cold, so come 'n warm your feet.
Okay.
Here. A souvenir for ya.
Really?
Gonna cut it into a pen?
Yep.
There.
Oh, it works, it works.
It works.
It looked like a heron, but I was way down south
when I came across her.
I didn't know they migrated.
Right?
Back in Eba, they just stood in the river year-round.
Yeah, they were all over, back in Eba.
Oh, it's no use.
I can't quite get it right.
Even you have those kind of moments?
Wait, don't tell me...
You haven't drawn in a while?
Well...
That painting of white rabbit waves...
Oh, that.
It caused a heap of trouble.
What?
Really?
You forgot?
Huh?
Our teacher entered it into a contest.
Everyone loved that painting,
and I didn't know what to do.
They all thought I'd made it,
when the real artist
was actually you.
Suzu, you're awful warm.
Suzu, you're awful soft,
and sweet.
Mizuhara-san...
It feels like I've been waiting for this day forever.
You coming for me...
You finally being here.
But I...
I'm just so angry at him! It makes my blood boil!
I'm sorry. I'm so sorry.
You...
love him, don't you?
Yep.
You really are just a ordinary girl.
I'm sorry.
You still get angry and sorry
about ordinary things.
You sure you don't want me
to take you back home?
I thought you were forced to get married
and needed help.
No...
All good, then.
Is he four years older?
Shusaku-san?
He'd be the same age as my late brother.
Our family was poor, so he went off
to a tuition-free naval academy.
And when my brother died,
I signed up to join the Navy.
They were just ordinary choices,
but somewhere along the way,
I guess my life derailed from the ordinary.
That's why...
I'm relieved to see that
you haven't changed a bit.
So don't just honor me as a dead soldier
when I'm gone.
Smile when you think of me.
I want you to stay ordinary and
honest in this world until the end.
Suzu.
You've become a real doll.
You idiot!
Ever since we were children, I've never
been able to tell you how I really feel.
Welcome home.
But why did they send us a single rock
instead of his bones.
It was so tiny that Sumi-chan thought...
Is this Onii-chan's brain?
Huh?
...and was all puzzled about it.
Makes me wonder what he was like.
They called us up in the cold for a stupid rock?
I should've guessed Yoichi
wouldn't die that easy.
People are gone just like that.
Our voices can't reach those no longer with us.
Shusaku-san.
I wanted to thank you for the other day.
Huh?
For giving me the time to talk to Mizuhara-san.
It's nothing.
But Shusaku-san,
doesn't marriage mean more to you?
I'm the one who forced you to marry me.
And yet you've never once
shown me your angry face.
I'm showing it to you now!
Oh, so now you're mad?
You need to pay attention!
Oh yeah?
Why'd you have to wear
the socks with holes today?!
The ones you sewed last night were too tight!
You've got others!
Hey, you two, do you really
need to fight right now?
You're going the wrong way again.
It's this way!
I know.
Our house is over there,
toward Mt. Haigamine.
I said I know!
It snowed a lot that winter.
I couldn't wait for spring to come.
The big blue sky,
more vivid than indigo.
It opens right up,
white roses blooming everywhere.
Like wallpaper,
going on forever.
Don't worry. No teacher will scold
a well-behaved child like you.
Really? School isn't scary?
Nope. You'll make friends too.
Just look at me. I was all alone
when I came here,
but now I'm the best of friends with everyone!
Even my mommy?
Well, uh...
Protect your head!
Harumi-chan!
If only I had some paint with me now.
No, what on earth am I thinking?
Hey!
What are you doing?
Quick! Get down and take cover!
Welcome home!
Oh, so now they sound the alarm?
Stay still. Watch out for shrapnel.
Ouch!
What a roar.
Huh?
Our 2,000 horsepower engines
sound wonderful.
That's why we work day and night at the factory
to perfect their performance.
We've come a long way from the
Type 91 engines with 500 horsepower.
We strive to improve our skills.
A light of hope for world peace.
A unified determination and goal...
So, what about the enemies horsepower?
So, what about the enemies horsepower...?
Father?
Air raid all clear!
I know you worked all night and it's been warm,
but how could you fall asleep
in the middle of a bombing?
There, there.
I was so scared.
A lot of fish were caught in Kure that day.
It's tiny.
It'll be big if you just draw it bigger.
Air raid alert! Air raid alert!
Ready air raid gear!
Put out all fires!
Remove sliding doors!
Grab survival kits and head to bomb shelters!
Air raid all clear!
It's still raw...
That poor, poor woman.
She lost her husband in the war.
And now her 17-year-old is being drafted.
Congratulations.
Ready air raid gear!
Put out the fire!
Remove sliding doors!
Survival kits...
I can't see anything.
Ouch!
Oops! Sorry!
W-Whose cat is that?!
I'm tired of sirens.
Never seen that before.
Enemy aircraft, 17 large fighters.
Currently above Mt. Tsuburayama.
Shots fired. Engagement ongoing.
30 aircraft approaching from
southeast Tokushima.
Heading towards Kure.
Air raid all clear!
May 5th, morning. Air raid.
125 large enemy aircraft attacked.
Damage to Hiro Naval Arsenal and
Air Arsenal No. 11 was very limited.
I'm home.
Good. You're safe, Shusaku.
Where's Dad?
Not home... yet.
Oh.
Suzu-san, it's boiling over.
You're so small, Suzu-san.
You're small even when you stand.
What is it?
Nothing.
You're small. That's all.
Your father's okay. I'm sure of it.
My military uniform arrived.
What?
It's wrapped up there.
From the 15th, I'll be a Chief Petty Officer.
I'll go to Navy training
and won't be back for three months.
Will you come back after training?
I think so.
But you'll be okay, Suzu-san.
You're small and thin,
but you can protect this house all on your own.
I can't.
That's impossible!
I'm sorry. That not true.
I love you.
But I might forget your face
after three months without you.
Suzu-san...
That's why I'll wait for you right here.
Because if I didn't,
I don't know if I could ever find you.
Will you remember me now?
Oh!
It was just a figure of speech.
No, with you, it's possible.
Let me see. How handsome do I look?
I can't show you. It's top secret!
Well, I'm off.
Take care.
Shusaku, I'll walk you halfway.
Thanks.
Your uniform looks so cool!
The house suddenly feels so much bigger.
For the Houjo-sans.
I thought he would've been admitted
to a hospital nearby.
No wonder we couldn't find him.
He's injured around his head and stomach,
but he'll be discharged soon.
Dad asked me to repair his watch.
It's a good chance to visit the Kuromura family
back in Shimonoseki tomorrow.
Huh?
Where my brother is?
I'll get ready.
Can I come?
What about school?
Don't worry.
They'd only have you doing exercises
and playing in the dirt.
The hands of girls
can also work for our country.
We are all...
This will take forever.
Aw...
I'll get the tickets.
Can you take Harumi to see Dad?
Huh?
All right. Let's go, Harumi-chan.
Can we go see all the Navy ships?
Sure.
This sure isn't like you!
Push comes to shove,
just pull out your bamboo spear!
You idiot! I'm not scared of ex-in-laws!
Well, you seemed out of sorts,
so I thought for sure...
And use a bamboo spear for what?
Is Shimonoseki far?
Yep.
Farther than Hiroshima?
Way farther.
This way?
You have to stay quiet, okay?
Is this the enemy's music?
Sorry to worry you.
I've been unconscious.
I hear it's June already.
I'm just glad you're alive.
We're gonna ride the train and see my brother.
Is that so? Well, the sooner the better.
Hey, what ship did you ride?
Auxiliary Minesweeper No. 16.
I've picked up bits and pieces of news lying here.
The Hiro Naval Arsenal was closed down,
and there are rumors
that we'll be merged with the Army.
Suzu-san, did you know that the Yamato sunk?
The Yamato?
That's right. Backed into a corner,
she went out with her guns blazing.
The Seto Inland Sea is no longer ours.
Which means
the white rabbits are...
Huh?
Really? Is it really?
Nothing.
That's why I told Keiko
to ask the Kuromuras to let Harumi
stay with them for the time being.
It's safer.
So that's why she was...
Hey, Suzu-san, can we go that way?
I want to see what ships are here
so I can tell my brother.
Hmm, I wonder if we can see anything.
Just a peek! Just a peek!
We can't see anything.
Oh no. What should we do?
No time to make it back home.
We need to find a public bomb shelter.
Huh?
Are they really coming?
We've had so many false alarms.
0923 hours, enemy planes sighted
southeast of Tokuyama.
Roughly 20 large aircraft heading to Kure.
Oh dear, so they're really coming this time.
Excuse me, could you let us in?
Of course. Quickly.
Evacuate! Run!
Suzu-san, I'm scared.
We'll be okay.
Look.
That's Mommy.
Uh-huh. And who's this?
Me.
Harumi-chan, your mommy's always with you.
You aren't from around here, are you?
We came from Naganoki to visit the hospital.
Bad timing, huh?
It's coming! Cover your ears and open your mouth
or else your eyes will pop out!
It's so hot...
Hang on.
Excuse me. Can we have some water?
Thank you very much.
Did we miss the train?
Maybe the train's waiting for people.
Okay.
Aw, I can't see anything.
Are you all right?
Yes!
Unexploded bombs
might just be delayed time bombs.
You need to evacuate now!
Sure! Thank you for your hard work!
Hey Suzu-san?
Will you draw my brother sometime?
Craters of unexploded bombs are small.
According to the latest civil defense
and combat operations reports,
the enemy is also dropping these bombs...
Watch out, Harumi-chan!
Not again. Another mistake.
I
You
ll never get married if you can
t do it right.
I
She warned me so many times,
but somehow I was okay.
Watermelon.
Warabi-mochi.
Mint candy.
I wish there had been a ditch we could jump into.
I held my bag with my left hand.
And Harumi-san with my right hand.
If only I had it the other way around.
I should've run barefoot.
Over the hill...
What was over there, anyway?
That's the Tone and that's the Hyuga.
Look, Mommy. It's the Yamato.
She...
She resembles Shusaku-san so much.
You were there with her.
How could you let this happen?
I'm sorry.
I'm so sorry, Harumi-san.
I'm so sorry, Onee-san.
Murderer.
You killed her!
Stop, Keiko.
Give her back!
It's time for the tofu rationing.
She's not herself right now.
She didn't mean what she said.
We're glad that we got you back alive, at least.
Really?
Places to belong don't go away so easy.
Rin-san?
Right?
At that moment, where was it that I belonged?
That wooden fence should've had some gaps.
If only the blast took me, and I got through...
To the other side, to the other side...
Oh no, not again.
Ignore the siren. They won't come.
This house made it through, huh?
That it did. Don't you worry.
I'm glad.
That's a lie.
That lady we saw.
Her house was completely destroyed.
What better excuse is there
to leave this town than that?
Don't push yourself.
Well, if it gets too tiring at work,
I'll just take a break there.
Be safe.
Oh, good. The sun's out.
I think I'll hang the bandages out to dry.
Chugoku region air raid information.
2350 hours. Enemy aircraft in Hiroshima Bay,
Suo-Nada Sea, and Bungo Channel.
Are you able to get up, Suzu-san?
Yes.
Dozens of other formations
northwest of Shikoku.
I'm okay.
2358 hours. Enemy aircraft
circling Kure and Hiroshima.
There's so many of them,
but I can't see a single one.
Are those flares?
Hurry, Suzu-san! Come on!
Eighth squad, move!
Suzu-san, what are you doing?
Hurry!
Suzu-san?
Suzu-san?!
Suzu-san! Is that a bomb?
Water! We need more water!
Okay. Let's do it.
Chugoku region air raid information.
Easy does it.
0020 hours. The enemy formation
that was in the Bungo Channel
Be careful.
is advancing northbound via Hiroshima Bay.
Another formation northbound
via Bungo Channel.
Three are confirmed in the seas south of Ashizuri.
End of information bulletin.
This is JOFK, Hiroshima Broadcasting.
Hang on, people of Kure!
Persevere, people of Kure!
To anyone suffering hardship,
we've been given rice balls from Hiroshima!
Come get them at Nikou Park!
Where can I file a damage report?
Is City Hall still standing?
My house burned down.
Avoiding the shelter saved us.
Mind if I use these?
No. Go ahead.
Oh, here. Eat up while it's still warm.
My house burnt down, but the potatoes
I stored under the floor cooked.
Oh, thank you.
Onee-san, do you...
I'm beat. It's so, so hot.
Hey! Anyone here from Shinonome?
We can't go south to Asahi town.
Even the red-light district burned to the ground.
I see.
Suzu-san!
You're hurt.
Your training?
Canceled.
I'm just glad that you're alive.
As I faded away...
Suzu-san!
I heard myself say, “I need to find Rin-san.”
Stay with me, Suzu-san!
I'm just glad...
I'm glad your fever's coming down.
Boy, I'm glad it was a dud.
I'm glad it was extinguished.
I'm glad you're recovering so quickly.
I'm glad.
I don't know what I should be glad about.
The right hand that held Harumi-san's hand
in June.
The right hand that drew Shusaku-san's face
in May.
The right hand that held Teru-san's lip balm
in April.
The right hand that held my brother's brain
in February.
The right hand that botched
my sister-in-law's kimono last November.
The right hand that drew a watermelon
for Rin-san last August.
The right hand that cooked Lord Kusunoki's rice.
The right hand that drew...
The right hand that drew my hometown
last February.
The hand that loved to make nori.
The right hand that drew many rabbits
seven years ago.
Your sister is here!
What a disaster, Suzu-chan.
Sumi-chan, I'm surprised you could make it.
A nice army officer gave me a lift
on the relief truck.
What's that?
It's not new, but it's pure cotton.
Not rayon?
That's right, so it's strong.
Wow!
Thank you.
These are loquats from up on Mt. Eba.
You sure you're okay?
I need to exercise.
Let me walk you halfway.
I'm supposed to meet him
in front of the fire station.
That's near the turret by the river.
Or did that burn down too?
It's still there.
The army officer showed it to me
when I first arrived.
He's young but very kind.
He's the one who's been
giving me meal tickets.
He even remembered that I have an older sister
who got married and moved to Kure.
You like him, huh?
Oh please, Suzu-chan!
Ouch.
This is horrible.
It's so sad that Kure keeps being targeted.
You must find it hard to be part of that home
while not being able to do housework.
Hey Suzu-chan, why don't you
come home to Hiroshima?
Huh?
The bombings aren't as bad.
And with our ogre brother gone,
there'll be no one to pick on you.
I suppose...
Maybe I will if your officer friend
turns out to be quite the handsome one.
Why, that's so improper!
I'm kidding! I'm kidding!
See you soon!
Something's wrong.
It'd be great if you came.
The festival in Eba will be early next month,
so come home soon, okay?
Thanks, Sumi-chan.
I'm glad that my brother is dead.
I'm the one that's gone all wrong.
Like a drawing using my left hand.
Oh well, here we go again.
It's going to be a long day. Pack everything.
Ow, that's hot!
Suzu-san, come on!
Don't come here.
This isn't the place for you right now.
That's right! Fly as far away as you can!
Over the mountain, to Hiroshima!
Are you trying to die?
I'm sorry. I just...
I just saw a heron flying.
It must've come from the waterfront.
Shusaku-san, I'm...
going home to Hiroshima.
For good?
Is this about your hand?
The air raids?
Harumi?
Yes.
Yes, it's all of those things.
Say something!
You're wrong!
Tell me why, then!
Suzu-san, I really enjoyed these 18 months
we spent together.
I loved coming home to you.
I loved walking with you
and listening to you talk.
You don't feel the same?
Am I still a stranger to you?!
I can't hear you.
I can't hear you! I can't hear you!
I can't hear anything!
I'm going home!
I'm going home to Hiroshima!
Oh, is that so?!
Do as you please!
No enemy aircraft over the
Chugoku military district.
0731 hours, Hiroshima Prefecture.
Air raid warning lifted.
Great timing.
Okay, we're off.
'Kay.
Take care.
Oh, ahhhh...
That's the spot.
My word. What a hot morning.
Things will be much lonelier
without you around, Suzu-san.
So? When's your appointment?
Huh?
With the doctor.
Oh, about 10 o'clock.
You need to change.
Here.
Excuse me, um...
Oh, right. I guess this isn't going in our wash.
Isn't your hometown's festival today?
Yes. I was going to go home last weekend,
but I couldn't get an appointment until today.
Don't look!
Sorry.
You'll never make it, anyway.
Doctors are busy, you know.
They'll probably have to write you a referral
to somewhere in Hiroshima too.
Not like you could buy train tickets, anyway.
Here.
I've fixed up that pure cotton outfit
your sister brought.
I added elastic straps
so you can put it on yourself.
They're all I could scrape together.
Thank you very much.
I'm sorry I blamed you for Harumi's death.
It's okay.
The man I loved died young.
My shop was destroyed.
I can't see my children anymore.
But my choices have led me here.
You had no choice, though.
You were brought here
to marry into a family you didn't know.
You just did what you were told.
What a boring life that must be.
You're welcome to stay here
or go anywhere you choose.
Don't worry about what others think,
just choose for yourself.
Keiko-chan, did you see that flash?
I did!
Could it be lightning in this weather?
Um, now that I think about it,
can you wash this, please?
And please, would you let me stay?
Okay! Okay! Now let me go.
It's too hot for that!
What was that?
Nothing. The JOFK isn't coming in.
The other stations?
Hey!
Come over here and look at this!
What is that cloud?
Cloud?
Look at that big cloud. It's an anvil cloud.
This is Okayama Broadcasting.
Hiroshima, do you read me?
This is Okayama Broadcasting...
I found a community notice
all the way from Hiroshima on the street.
Anyone available, please come
to the settlement house.
Chita-san, you're a nurse, aren't you?
Yes, but I've never made sandals.
I doubt anyone around here has.
Is this how you do it?
Uh-huh.
Oh, it's so frustrating with one hand.
Are you gloating?
So what're you going to do
with all these sandals?
Send 'em to Hiroshima.
That flash melted the roads,
so regular shoes are no good.
Can I come too?
The wounded must stay.
My son is a soldier
who'd been sent to Hiroshima.
Then you can join us tomorrow.
When we were being bombed,
Hiroshima helped us out,
so now it's our turn to...
My hair's no longer in the way.
So take me, please.
I said no!
Silly girl. I'll trim your hair when we get home.
My husband has business in Hiroshima soon.
I hear it was a new type of bomb.
Oh no.
Suzu-san, I'm sure your family...
Mom!
The navy base sent a relief party.
But...
You came from Hiroshima too?
He died sitting here?
He walked all the way from Hiroshima.
But we couldn't tell who he was.
His face and clothes had melted.
Let's not tell Mrs. Houjo-san.
I can hardly look at the poor girl in the eye.
I feel so bad.
I picked some eucalyptus leaves.
Please use it as a mosquito repellent.
Thank you.
Stay strong, okay?
Okay.
And by the way, Urano Juro, Kiseno,
and Sumi are from Eba.
And also Morita Ito, Marina,
and Chizuko are from Kusatsu.
I want to stay strong.
Kind but strong.
Like the people of this town.
Ah, this rubbish again.
We'll never give in to violence.
Please let me stay forever.
You had me worried. You dummy.
Dummy, dummy, dummy, dum...
I'm sorry.
I'm really sorry.
Sorry!
I missed all of them.
I'd never hear the end of it if the Navy knew.
Suzu-san, if this U.S. propaganda isn't handed in,
the MPs again are gonna chew you out again.
They're just going to burn them, anyway.
But this way, we can make
better use of them as toilet paper.
That's true enough.
But we can't let people
use our toilet for a while, then.
Scrounging up whatever we can to survive.
That's our battle.
Oh, please come in.
Thank you.
The thought of those officers who have fallen in the
fields of battle, those who died at their posts of duty,
or those who met an untimely death,
and all their bereaved families,
pains our heart night and day.
The welfare of the wounded
and the war-sufferers,
and of those who have
lost their homes and livelihood...
We have resolved to pave the way for a grand peace
for all generations to come,
by enduring the unendurable
and suffering what is unsufferable.
Thus ends His Majesty the Emperor's
honorable broadcast.
It's finally over.
So, this means...
We lost the war?
Why?
They dropped those new bombs
on Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
The Soviets joined the war,
so we couldn't possibly win.
They knew what we were getting into,
didn't they?
I thought we were fighting to the last man!
There's five of us still here!
I still have my left arm, and both my legs!
Harumi.
H-Harumi...
Everything we've done just slips away.
Everything that made us think it would be okay.
All the reasons why we endured it all.
Oh, I see.
Rice and soybeans we took from overseas.
That's what my body is made of.
So we give in to violence?!
Oh, how I wish I could have just died an
innocent daydreamer, blind to all that!
I tucked this away for our last meal.
Let's enjoy white rice tonight.
But not all of it.
We still have tomorrow and the day after that.
August 15th and 16th...
The 17th too.
September.
October, November and next year.
A year later, ten years later.
Forever and ever.
Look, it's a glorious white!
We only have rice.
Not to worry.
Where's Shusaku?
Not home yet.
I suppose it's the legal office's job
to maintain order in times like this.
Let's just start eating.
No more bombs so no more floating fish.
I remember that time, yes.
What're we doing?
I can't see my beautiful white rice.
They'll be landing soon.
I'll be transferred to Otake.
Until the navy is disbanded, it'll be up to us
to maintain law and order, whatever the sacrifice.
Ah, it's at times like this...
that I wish I had both hands,
so I could hold his hand to comfort him.
It's so quiet.
Everyone's well prepared.
Thank you. Here is fine.
Okay.
Quick, head back home.
Goodbye.
I'll be back! I'll come home to you, got it?
Yes!
We haven't had salt or soy sauce for a while.
Oh, Onee-san!
Oh, Suzu-san. Do you know what this line is for?
No idea, but I'll take anything right now
since we're short on everything.
That's true enough.
This city sure has changed.
Wonder if Hisao begs for chocolate too.
Would Harumi have done the same?
It's just the leftovers of the occupation army.
Paper scraps?
So... So... So...
So delicious!
No flavor to be found up here.
I gave the Americans directions,
and they gave me chocolate.
With that hairstyle,
they probably thought you were a child.
You sure about this?
You're trading away so many clothes.
It's all right.
Didn't you hear?
The dead soldier found next to the
settlement house was my son.
I couldn't recognize my own son.
And you lost Harumi-san right in front of your eyes.
Yes...
It was awful.
Suzu.
Smile when you think of me.
I want you to stay ordinary and
honest in this world until the end.
Suzu.
Harumi-san. I can see the ship now.
It's the Aoba.
Tetsu-san, I just saw it
..in the corner of your smile...
The place where the white rabbits hop across the sea
and the white herons fly across the sky.
Harumi-san always laughed,
so I'll smile whenever I think of her.
From now on, this body will be here to smile.
That's right. It'd be a waste to cry all the time.
It's a waste of salt.
Thank heavens for the salty seas!
Grandma! Auntie! Chizuko-chan!
Oh, goodness me.
Suzu-chan!
Sumi-chan?
Oh, Suzu-chan! You cut your hair.
Don't get up. Are you ill?
I'm just a little dizzy.
Oh no.
Oh, my regret knows no bounds.
I can't help with work outside
on this day of bitter cold.
I suppose you must rest easy for now.
Oh, if only I had my hand, I'd draw
“My Ogre Brother's Adventures in the South Seas.”
What would the story be about?
Our brother's troop transport gets shipwrecked...
So he builds a house with palm leaves
on an island.
He grows a beard and marries a crocodile.
A crocodile for a bride, you say?
I wish he could come back to Eba.
And Mom too.
What?
On the morning of the festival,
Mom went shopping in the city.
Dad and I looked everywhere
but we couldn't find her.
Dad fell ill in October and died quickly after.
He was cremated along with others at school.
I should have told you sooner.
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry I couldn't come sooner.
I'm glad you didn't.
Suzu-chan, look at me.
Will I get better?
You will. It just wouldn't be right if you didn't.
Sachiko-san?
No.
Kiyoko-san! Aren't you Kiyoko-san?
Everyone lost someone, and they're still looking.
Sorry...
I think I saw Rin-san a few times too.
Suzu-san.
You're back safe and sound.
The Navy was disbanded
at the end of November.
I've been let go.
Suzu-san, this is the bridge
where I first met you.
We can't go back in time.
We'll keep changing and growing,
this city and us.
But I'll always be able to spot you, Suzu-san.
I'll find that beauty mark
and know it's you right away.
Shusaku-san, thank you for finding me
in this corner of the world.
And please, never leave,
and always be by my side.
Leave it.
I'm glad I found a job in Hiroshima.
Yeah.
Still, it's an awfully long way to commute.
I...
Huh?
Thank you. But you can eat it.
We could leave Kure and start over here.
It might be good for Sumi-san
and the rest of your family.
No, I don't mind the commute.
I'm worried about Hiroshima,
but Kure is the town I've chosen to belong to.
Oh?
Kure.
Kure?
That's right. This is Kure.
“Kure” means we are protected
by nine mountains.
On your right is Mt. Yasumi.
To the left is Mt. Hachimaki.
And in the center is Mt. Haigamine.
That's where our home is.
This child...
Oh dear.
She's covered in lice!
Quick, get some water boiling.
We have to boil all of her clothes!
We should start with a bath.
I think it's best that she go in last.
I'll start the fire.
I wonder if Harumi's clothes would be too small.